

# EDUCATION PhD STUDENT IN SOCIOLOGY

The Ohio State University

# MASTER OF SCIENCE IN PUBLIC HEALTH

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

# BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN COMMUNITY HEALTH

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

SAS Programming 1 SQL

## MARQUIANNA GRIFFIN

mqgriffi@gmail.com

#### **QUALIFICATIONS SUMMARY**

Experienced professional who employs strong analytic, quality improvement, and strategic planning skills in maintaining accurate administrative data. Driven leader with proven success managing research assistants, co-constructing databases, evaluating program implementation, and securing revenue from data reporting.

#### **TECHNOLOGY SUMMARY**

Operating Systems: Windows, Unix Programming Languages: SQL, R, SAS

Database Management: MS Access, FileMaker Pro, SPSS

Tools: Visio, RedCAP, Adobe Live Cycle, Cornerstone, Centricity/Epic EHR

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Data and Research Technology Liaison Chapin Hall at the University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

2014 - 2019

Acts as liaison between agencies to foster collaboration around data permissions, and coordinates data activities including acquisition, processing, analysis, and review.

- Developed Statistical Analysis System (SAS) code to process and de-identify Chicago Public Schools data in Unix environment and debugged programs (representative of ~400,000 student records)
- Reviewed procedures, data collection, analyses, and findings of technical reports
- Streamlined the process surrounding acquiring data permissions and securing data (e.g. educational, Medicaid), which resulted in timely turnaround for Principal Investigators' projects
- Performed organization's first Data Sharing Agreement (DSA) review, developed organization's first DSA report, and utilized results to promote compliance and disseminate first ever annual data report to 25% of the organization's partner agencies
- Contributed to the development of 5 policies implemented organization-wide around security, compliance, data receipt, and external access to data holdings
- Aided in completion of organization's first security risk assessment, representative of >300 security controls

#### Research Data Manager

#### Northwestern University, Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL

2012 - 2014

Responsible for management and analysis of Illinois Department of Juvenile Justice data within the Department's large-scale administrative databases.

- Cleaned and produced descriptive analysis on admissions, exits and stock population data extracts (representative of over 1,000 unique annual records) in SPSS
- Graphed and completed comparative analyses on quantitative data (>2000 reportable incidents and juvenile confinement records) that captured fiscal year/calendar year trends
- Utilized statistical practices to create confinement index, a systematic method to compare confinement statewide
- Designed 3 data reporting tools to capture data on juvenile parole as well as youth with placement barriers
- Recommended design changes to existing reporting system to contribute to more efficient reporting outputs
- Assisted in graduate curriculum of Loyola University students, as well publications of the Bureau
  of Justice Statistics, US Census Bureau, and the Illinois Criminal Justice Information Association
- Collaborated with DJJ team to produce the Department's first large scale monthly data report



#### **VOLUNTEER WORK**

Child Friend 2014 - 2017

Educational Leader 1999 - 2001, 2010 - 2012 2013 - 2017

#### **ADDITIONAL**

Association of Maternal and Child Health Programs CityLeader

AmeriCorps Alumni

#### **Project Manager**

#### Access Community Health Network, Chicago, IL

Created surveys, collected and analyzed data, and conducted program evaluation to best support the Maternal and Child Health Department.

- Successfully managed program data sets (over 100,000 patient records), and created internal publications and health education materials
- Created report that yielded more than \$100,000 in revenue from inpatient delivery charges
- Co-constructed database with IT department as well as provided technical assistance re: program reporting of quality measures and electronic data processing operations, which generated organizational revenue
- Improved departmental metrics through data analysis and reporting
- Negotiated pricing with vendors re: Access database build as well as AutoData Scanning System
- Conducted patient quantitative interviews (> 300 interviews) and quantitative needs assessment surveys (> 2 dozen assessments) that contributed to hospital infrastructural changes and the inception of a social service program for males
- Assisted in the evaluation of Westside Healthy Start, which led to programmatic adjustments by program's stakeholders
- Supervised 3 research assistants in collecting/disseminating program data to refine their public health/research experiences

### Data Coordinator/Youth Advocate Leader Lawndale Christian Health Center (LCHC), Chicago, IL

2009 - 2010

2010 - 2012

Served LCHC Maternal and Child Health patient population through data reporting, case management and supervision of youth participants of the Lawndale Summer Youth Project.

- Composed data reports for internal and federal stakeholders, which secured grant funding and generated organizational revenue
- Acted as liaison between patients and providers, which promoted a team approach to improving healthcare
- Contributed to quarterly evaluation of case managers
- Secured insurance coverage for over 50 patients with a proven record of reconciling subsequent issues related to coverage
- Supervised 2 youth advocate leaders to create professional development for 30 youth within the areas of health, science and technology
- Developed and implemented professional maturation activities for 30 youth that resulted in medical, social and technical competence

#### **PRESENTATIONS/PUBLICATIONS**

Clay, S. L., Griffin, M., & Averhart, W. (2019, November). Racial/ethnic socioeconomic disparities and birth outcomes in pregnant women in the United States: An examination of risk factors associated with racial identity. In APHA's 2019 Annual Meeting and Expo (Nov. 2-Nov. 6). American Public Health Association.

Loggins-Clay, S., Griffin, M., & Averhart, W. (2018). Black/White Disparities in Pregnant Women in the United States: An examination of risk factors associated with Black/White racial identity. *Health & Social Care in the Community*.

Griffin, M. "Is access to primary healthcare the solution we have been searching for regarding emergency department utilization differences between minority and non-minority patients?" American Public Health Association Conference, Washington, DC, October 2011.

Griffin, M., Harvey, I. S., & Notaro, S. J. "Comparative Analysis of Emergency Department Utilization among Minority and Non-minority Clients within a Free Health Center," University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, Champaign, IL, August 2009.